Okay, today's דף daf פ"א *Daf Peh Aleph*, 81. We had discussed
yesterday, we had wrapped up the discussion about the father's contribution in
the animal kingdom, and we had moved on to the next משנה
mishnah, *Mishnah*, or actually to the end of the discussion of the
משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*, and we were looking at the fact that a
number of times the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* talks about being חייב chayav?
*chayav* for אותו ואת בנו Oto ve’et beno *Oto Ve'et Beno*, even
if the first or the second שחיטה shechita *shechitah* does not make
the meat permissible, which is called שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uyah.
*shechitah she'eina re'uyah*. And the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* points out that this
is against רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbi Shimon's* position that says שחיטה
שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uyah *shechitah she'eina re'uyah* does not count as
a שחיטה shechita *shechitah*. And actually the next משנה mishnah *Mishnah* that's
coming up that we're going to see later today has that position
explicitly spelled out. So far then, we've established the issue of שחיטה
שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uyah. *shechitah she'eina re'uyah*, and then we went
on to say also that interestingly that applies even to קדשים Kodashim,
*Kodashim* because the שחיטה shechita. *shechitah* does not make the meat immediately
permissible, which was a little bit surprising and we're going to revisit
that later today. And the other point to note is that the
שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'eina re'uyah. *shechitah she'eina re'uyah*, the relevance was
not just on the second שחיטה shechita. *shechitah* for the obligation of
אותו ואת בנו Oto ve’et beno *Oto Ve'et Beno*, but for the
first שחיטה shchita. *shechitah* as well, because you're only חייב chayav *chayav*
if both animals are שחט shecht *shachted*, and if the first animal
was considered a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shchita she'eina re'uya. *shechitah she'eina re'uyah*
because it was קדשים kodshim *Kodashim* in general or because of some
other reason, it was a קדשים kodshim חוץ למזבח *Kodashim chutz lamizbe'ach*—חוץ
למקדש *chutz lamikdash*—but even any of those issues, even if the first
one is not considered a שחיטה shchita, *shechitah*, the person would be
exempt. So our משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* was not רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rebbi Shimon*. Now we're looking at the other question which is why
when you שחט shecht *shacht* קדשים kodshim, *Kodashim*, the second one and
it's אותו ואת בנו Oto ve’et beno *Oto Ve'et Beno*, why don't
you also transgress not bringing an animal
the prohibition which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* learns out from the verse
of לא ירצה *lo yeratzeh*, shall not be accepted, which they understand
means you're not allowed to bring as a קרבן korban *korban*, to
שחט shecht *shacht* to bring as any קרבן korban. *korban* that will
not be accepted. So since this second animal won't be accepted today
because you're not allowed to bring it and it's considered מחוסר זמן
Mechusar Zman *mechussar zman*, so therefore in the act of bringing it,
you should transgress that prohibition and not just the prohibition of אותו
ואת בנו Oto ve’et beno, *Oto Ve'et Beno*. So the first answer
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said is you're right, you do, you do
get מלקות malkos. *malkos* for that, the משנה mishna *Mishnah* just didn't
bother mentioning it because you were already getting one set of מלקות
malkos. *malkos*. Now we pick up with another answer to that question.
So it's the very bottom of דף פ' עמוד ב' amud beis,
*Daf Peh Amud Beis* and we say the following. רבי זירא
אמר amar, *Rebbi Zeira amar*, the last line, middle of the line
by the asterisk, רבי זירא *Rebbi Zeira* says, הנך למחוסר זמן דכתיב
נתקו לעשה *hanach limechussar zman dekativ nitko le'asei*. This prohibition of bringing
an animal before its right time or any animal that is not
fit is not you don't get מלקות malkos *malkos* for it because
it's connected to a positive מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*. What positive מצוה Mitzvah
*mitzvah* is it? Or at least the specific problem of when it's
not its right time, which is in the תורה Torah *Torah* explicitly
when it's not eight days old and the חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* understand
it includes also the animal that can't be שחט shechting *shachted* today
because its mother was שחט shecht *shachted*, so it's not its right
time because you have to wait till tomorrow. מה טעמא *Mai ta'ama*?
דאמר קרא d'amar kra, *De'amar Kra*, the verse says, מיום השמיני והלאה
ירצה *Miyom hashmini vahal'ah yeratzeh*,
from the eighth day it shall be desirable as a קרבן korban
*korban*. So that is a positive מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*, the same way
we interpreted לא ירצה *lo yeratzeh* as not just being descriptive but
as actually being a prohibition: you shall not try to make it
desirable, you shall not bring it as a קרבן korban *korban*. This
is being interpreted as a positive מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*. You shall bring
it as a קרבן korban *korban*, or if you were somehow
planning you were going to transgress, here's the way to not transgress,
to wait till the eighth day. מיום השמיני אין מעיקרא לא *Miyom
hashmini in, me'ikara lo*. You can only bring it starting on day
eight, not originally. לאו lav, הבא מכלל עשה עשה *Lav haba miklal
aseh aseh*,
and since it is implicitly prohibiting you to bring it before the
eighth day, but it is only implicitly prohibiting it, the prohibition is
implicit from a positive framing, the positive framing is you shall bring
it on the eighth day, so the implicit is don't bring it
before, but the status of that commandment is a positive מצוה mitzvah,
*mitzvah*. It is a positive מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* because it's framed as
a positive, so bring it on the eighth day is a way
of saying don't bring it before, but ultimately it's a positive מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah*. Now the question is, why is this called a נתקו
לעשה *nitko le'asei*, a prohibition connected to a positive מצוה *mitzvah*? Normally
a prohibition connected to a positive מצוה *mitzvah* is when the positive
מצוה *mitzvah* is a way of fixing the prohibition. For example, don't
steal and if you steal return the object. Don't take the mother
bird on the children and if you do send the mother bird
free. Okay, don't leave meat over of a קרבן korban *korban* till
the next day and if you do burn it. Okay, those are
cases where there's a positive מצוה *mitzvah* that is coming to somewhat
rectify the consequences of your transgression. That is a classic example of
a negative prohibition that is a positive מצוה *mitzvah* that's connected to
a negative prohibition that you don't get מלקות malkos. *malkos* because the
positive
מצוה *mitzvah* somewhat ameliorates, right, somewhat fixes your transgression. That's not the
case here. Here, if I brought this קרבן korban. *korban* on day
seven, or if I brought this קרבן korban *korban* on the same
day the mother was שחט shecht. *shachted*, there's no way I can
fix it because you're telling me I have a positive מצוה *mitzvah*
to wait till tomorrow? If anything, that makes my sin worse. I
didn't only transgress the negative prohibition, I also transgressed the positive מצוה
*mitzvah*, right? And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* even says, it's a negative
prohibition that is derived... derives from a positive. Well, that's a way
of saying that it's more prohibited, not that the positive can fix
it. So תוספות Tosafot
*Tosefos* raises all these questions, and תוספות Tosafot *Tosefos* actually says that
the phrase here ניתקו לעשה *nitko l'aseh* does not have the meaning
that the עשה *aseh* is connected and fixes it. ניתקו *Nitko* can
also mean לנתק *lenatek* can mean to remove. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosefos*
here, and he brings other cases where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means
this, it means that the prohibition was the generic prohibition of לא
ירצה *lo yeratzeh* does not apply to this case because it was
particularly focused on, you know, articulated explicitly in this positive מצוה *Mitzvah*.
So meaning we have a generic prohibition, לא ירצה *lo yeratzeh*, don't
bring a קרבן korban, *Korban* which is not acceptable. We have one
case, one type of not acceptable קרבן korban *Korban* where the תורה
Torah *Torah* is very specific and very explicit. Wait till the eighth
day. So there where the תורה Torah *Torah* says wait till the
eighth day, the only prohibition you transgress when you don't wait till
the eighth day is the explicit prohibition, not the generic. Okay, and
that's why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here says that a negative that
derives from a positive is a positive. Yes, it's prohibited, but it's
only prohibited by a positive. But because here it is explicitly prohibited,
this idea of not the right time, we don't put it in
the generic category of don't bring anything that's not acceptable. So that's
the way תוספות Tosafos. *Tosefos* understands this answer. A קרבן korban *Korban*
that is מחוסר זמן Mechusar Zman. *mechusar zman*, not the right time,
either it's not yet the eighth day or you have to wait
until tomorrow because you slaughtered the mother today, is prohibited based on
this positive מצוה *Mitzvah* of wait till the eighth day, wait till
the right time, and is not prohibited based on the generic prohibition.
That's what תוספות Tosafot *Tosefos* says. רש״י Rashi *Rashi* tries to say
that this is the classic example of an עשה *aseh* fixing the
לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*, fixing the negative, but for all the reasons
I said, it's very bizarre. Number one is it doesn't really fix
it, there's no way it can fix it. And number two is
the very phrase of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
doesn't say this עשה *aseh* fixes. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says and
therefore you transgress this עשה *aseh*. It emphasizes the transgression here, not
the fixing of the עשה *aseh*. Okay, so that's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s answer. That's why you do not get transgress, get lashes for
bringing this קרבן korban *Korban* a day before its time. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just wraps this up. ומיבעי ליה לכדרבי אבתולקי *u'mibai
lei lich'derabi Avtulki*. You can't have, how can you use this verse
to say that you transgress this positive מצוה *Mitzvah*, you know, this
verse of on the eighth day bring it, to say you transgress
a positive מצוה *Mitzvah*? You need it to tell me what רבי
אבתולקי *Rabbi Avtulki* says. Why? דרבי אבתולקי רמי *D'Rabbi Avtulki rami*, רבי
אבתולקי *Rabbi Avtulki* showed a contradiction. כתיב *Kesiv*,
one verse says והיה שבעת ימים תחת אמו *vehaya shivat yamim tachat
imo*, it'll be seven days under its mother. This is an animal
obviously that you want to bring as a קרבן korban *Korban*. הלילה
חזי *Halaila chazi*, only seven days, by the night you know leading
into the eighth, presumably it's fit for a קרבן korban *Korban*. וכתיב
*U'chesiv*, and another verse says מיום השמיני והלאה ירצה *miyom hashmini va'halah
yeratzeh*, only day eight you can bring it, not the preceding night.
מיום השמיני והלאה אין *Miyom hashmini va'halah in*, from day eight onwards
yes, לילה לא *laila lo*, not the preceding night. הכיצד *Hakeitzad*? How
do you reconcile this? לילה לקדושה יום להרצאה *Laila likdusha yom l'hartza'ah*.
Because on the night before you can sanctify the animal, but you
can only bring the animal on the day. Now what is that
telling me? I know you can't bring animals at night, right? So
there's a general principle you can't bring animals at night. What's the
חידוש Chidush *chiddush* here? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* elsewhere where it
quotes this says the חידוש *chiddush* is not that you can't bring
it at night. The חידוש *chiddush* is that you can sanctify it
at night. I might have thought that since I can't bring it
tonight, right, that it's מחוסר זמן Mechusar Zman. *mechusar zman*, and since
it's מחוסר זמן *mechusar zman* it can't be sanctified because it's not
yet fit. Says no. Since tonight is connected till tomorrow, and tomorrow
it is going to be fit, it's considered to be enough its
right time that I can sanctify it. It can't be brought because
it's nighttime, but it's enough the right time that it can be
sanctified, which is a phrase the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses to say
לילה לאו lav? מחוסר זמן *laila lav mechusar zman*. The night before
is not considered to be not yet the right time. It is
the right time, you might not be able to bring it because
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash? *Beis HaMikdash* is only open for services
during the day, but because it's halakhically day eight, it's already considered
to be its time and therefore you can sanctify it.
Everything must be on the day before?
You right, the implication of that is you can't be מקדיש Makdish
*makdish* it on the day before. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosefos* asks on
that גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, there's a parallel גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* in זבחים
*Zevachim*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosefos* says he doesn't get it because he says
there are even גמרות *Gemaros* that say you can be מקדיש Makdish
*makdish* a fetus in its mother's womb. So since when can you
not be מקדיש *makdish* something just because it's not yet the right
time? So he doesn't have an answer there as a, it seems
that because of that question תוספות *Tosefos* at least here, there the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does seem to say that the חידוש *chiddush* is
that you can be, that you can be מקדיש *makdish*, that's what
you're allowed to do at night. תוספות *Tosefos* here says the חידוש
*chiddush* is that the night is prohibited. And what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is saying here is that the night is prohibited not just
because it's night, but also because it's still considered מחוסר זמן *mechusar
zman*, which is exactly the sort of opposite of the other גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. He says it is מחוסר זמן *mechusar zman* at night.
So then the question is, well, why do I care if you
can't bring it anyway? So תוספות *Tosefos* has, here's an, here's a
case where it matters, my gloss says not before you start a
במה Bamah. *bamah*. In a במה Bamah *bamah*, you're allowed to bring
קרבנות Korbanot *korbanos* at night, but you still can't bring קרבנות Korbanot
*korbanos*. considered מחוסר זמן, which is exactly the sort of opposite of
the other גמרא. Gemara He says it is מחוסר זמן at night.
So then the question is well why do I care if you
can't bring it anyway? So תוספות says here's an example, here's a,
here's a case where it matters. My תוספות says about the before
you started a במה. In a במה you're allowed to bring, you're
allowed to be, bring קרבנות Korbanot. at night but you still can't
bring קרבנות Korbanot. that are מחוסר זמן. Okay so anyway תוספות here
decides that he says that the, actually the חידוש is not that
you're allowed to be מקדיש it at night but that at night
it's still considered מחוסר זמן. But that's not what other גמרא Gemara
say about this. Okay, so that is, but yes, that's a good
question because we do normally assume you could be מקדיש an animal
before its time, just not bring it. All right, now the גמרא
Gemara goes on, so you see you need it for that and
not to tell you that there's a prohibition, a positive prohibition as
it were to wait till day eight. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no כתיב קרא אחרינא ksiv kra achrina for that we have another
verse to say that there's a positive מצוה to wait till day
eight. כן תעשה לשורך לצאנך. Ken ta’aseh lishorchecha litzonecha.
Okay, because the verse where it says wait till day eight says
again, repeats, so shall you do for your ox and your sheep.
So that's a positive מצוה and that positive מצוה which from, tells
you wait till day eight, don't bring it earlier. And again, therefore
we say you don't get lashes for it because it is only
prohibited based on this explicit positive מצוה and not based on a
generic prohibition of don't bring things that are not good קרבנות. Korbanot?
Okay, now we move on. Back to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shchita she'eina re'uya. אמר רב המנונא, Amar Rav Hamnuna,
רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna said, אמר היה רבי שמעון, Amar haya Rabbi
Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon used to say, אותו ואת בנו נוהג
בקדשים. Oto ve’et beno noheg b’kodashim. אותו ואת בנו Oto ve’et beno.
does not apply by קרבנות. Korbanot. This is a point that Charlie
made, right? If every שחיטה shchita? of a קרבן korban is basically
considered a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shchita she'eina re'uya. because the meat does
not become permissible right away, you have to sprinkle the blood. So
how you gonna ever have אותו ואת בנו Oto ve’et beno by
קרבנות? Korbanot. Whether it's the mother, the first animal that you're שוחט-ing
shochet or the second animal that you're שוחט-ing shochet that's a קרבן.
korban It's not one of them, it is not a שחיטה ראויה,
shechita re'uyah, so you'll never have it by
קרבנות. Korbanot, Okay, so
why? כיון דאמר, Keivan d'amar, what's the reason? כיון דאמר רבי שמעון,
Keivan d'amar Rabbi Shimon, שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה. Shechita she'eina
re'uyah lo shma shechita. A שחיטה shchita. that's not fit doesn't count
as a שחיטה. shchita, שחיטת קדשים נמי שחיטה שאינה ראויה היא. Shechitat
kodashim nami shechita she'eina re'uyah hi. So that also counts by קרבנות.
Korbanot Now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon never said it counts by קרבנות,
Korbanot but the גמרא gemara, has assumed it and here we're repeating
it. Since you can't eat the meat right away, it's a שחיטה
שאינה ראויה. shchita she'eina re'uya. We're going to see later that the
גמרא gemara is going to challenge this or have a different opinion
because, right, it makes sense, eventually you'll be able to eat the
meat and it's a necessary part of eating the meat. But now
we're claiming that it is not itself what create makes the meat
permissible all by itself. It's not sufficient, it might be necessary, and
therefore it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina reuya, And therefore you
can never have אותו ואת בנו osso ve'es beno by קרבנות korbanos?
because you'll never have a, something that counts as a שחיטה.
shechita Because חולין chullin we said that it could be ראויה re'uyah
if you just like immediately put it on the spit or something?
Because you know they have to drain the blood and all that.
It doesn't matter. It makes it permissible. Whether, oh, because oh, you
mean the איסור דם. issur dam. Two answers to that. One is,
okay, well not every part is, given. Two answers to that. One
is that you actually can eat the blood if it hasn't come
out of the meat. אומצא, umtza, you know, blood is only prohibited
if it comes out and then gets reabsorbed. Number one. So you
could in theory eat it raw. But number two, the point is
not just you can eat it immediately, but that every, but that
the meat is הלכתית halachically permissible. The blood might be forbidden, so
you have to, and the חלב chelev might be forbidden, so you
have to
get them out of the way, but the meat is totally כשר.
kosher. Whereas by קרבן korban when you שוחט shochet it, the meat
is not yet כשר. kosher. The meat is still forbidden to be
eaten and only becomes permissible through the זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. Okay?
So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara But this never says פיגול pigul then. So it would be
the same thing. Right.
But then everybody would agree. Then it's not a question. Then it
really is forbidden. Right. So now the גמרא says like this. Okay.
So מתיב רבא. Metiv Rava. רבא Rava asked on this. We have
a ברייתא braita and here's what the ברייתא braita says. This is
a ברייתא braita about the prohibition of קדשים בחוץ. kodashim bachutz. It
deals with the case of we're dealing about אותו ואת בנו, osso
ve'es beno but the focus is when do you transgress bringing a
sacrifice out of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash, So let's take a
look. Here's what the ברייתא braita says. אותו ואת בנו קדשים בחוץ.
Oto ve’et beno kodashim bachutz. Let's say you're bringing קרבנות korbanos. out
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but it's אותו ואת בנו. osso
ve'es beno? You're שוחט-ing shochet the mother and the child. So as
we've seen, the second therefore you can't transgress for the child because
it's not fit to be brought to be brought. It's because you're
not allowed to שוחט shochet it today. So what's the story with
that? So here's what the ברייתא braita says. רבי שמעון אומר שני
בלא תעשה. Rabbi Shimon omer sheni b'lo ta'aseh. Even though the second
one cannot be brought as a קרבן korban today because you שוחט-ed
shochet the mother. Okay, nevertheless and you don't get כרת. karet. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if you שוחט shochet a קרבן korban out
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. we've said until now that when
are you חייב? chayav You're only חייב chayav when it could be
brought in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually
splits and he says look, if it can't be brought today in
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you don't get כרת. karet. But if
it can be brought eventually in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, even
if not today, you still transgress a negative prohibition although you don't
get כרת. karet. So if you have a case of אותו ואת
בנו osso ve'es beno. and you're שוחט-ing shochet the second one out
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. you're not going to get כרת
karet because today you can't bring this animal as a קרבן korban.
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, says
you do get a לאו, lav, a negative prohibition, because and because
it will eventually be able to be a good קרבן. korban, So
let's take a look. So it says אמר רבי שמעון אומר שני
בלא תעשה. Amar Rabbi Shimon omer sheni b’lo ta’aseh. The second person
transgresses a negative prohibition. שהיה רבי שמעון אומר, Shehaya Rabbi Shimon omer,
because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon? used to say, כל הראוי לבוא לאחר
זמן, Kol hara’uy lavo l’achar zman, anything that could be a קרבן
korban at a later time, הרי הוא בלא תעשה, harei hu b’lo
ta’aseh, you do get its negative prohibition if you brought it as
a, you שוחט-ed shochet it out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
ואין בו כרת, Ve'ein bo kareis, but you don't get כרת kareis
because it's not fit today. It will be fit, but it's not
fit today, so split it. You get your prohibition, but you don't
get כרת. kareis. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the Sages say, "no, it's
all or nothing." כל שאין בו כרת אינו בלא תעשה, Kol she'ein
bo kareis eino belo ta'aseh, anything that you don't get כרת kareis
that cannot be brought today, you don't even transgress a negative prohibition.
Okay, now so now we've got an interesting thing though. Implicit in
this is that what does Rebbi Shimon say? Is it... do you
have a prohibition of אותו ואת בנו osso ve'es beno by קרבנות?
korbanos.
What's implicit? Is... does אותו ואת בנו osso ve'es beno. by קרבן,
korban are you prevented from shechting the second animal for the prohibition
of אותו ואת בנו? osso ve'es beno Yes, because Rebbi Shimon is
saying this second thing cannot be brought today. Why can't it be
brought today? Because of the restriction of אותו ואת בנו. osso ve'es
beno, So you have Rebbi Shimon basically saying אותו ואת בנו osso
ve'es beno, applies to קרבנות. korbanos And then he's like, oh, and
by the way, the implication of that is, is that you would
still get a prohibition of bringing the... of shechting a קרבן korban
out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, No כרת, kareis, but you
get a prohibition. חכמים Chachamim say you don't get a prohibition. But
we're all agreeing that this second animal that's a קרבן korban you
can't shecht today because you shechted the mother, right? Even though we...
so that's against our assertion that it does not apply by קרבנות.
korbanos, So let's take a look.
Now, וקשיא לן, Vekashya lan, we had a problem. קדשים בחוץ שני
בלא תעשה. Kodashim bachutz sheini belo ta'aseh. If you really want to
apply the position of Rebbi Shimon that... you know, שחיטה שאינה ראויה.
shechita she'eina reuya So why are we saying the second guy only
gets a negative prohibition? What should we really say? קמא, Kama, the
first guy who brought the first קרבן korban whether in or out
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, מכתש קטיל, miktash katil, we said
that shechting a קרבן korban is not considered שחיטה. shechita, It's like
you just killed it, not like you
shechted. And so the first... that's the first guy. שני, Sheini, so
once the first guy didn't do what counts as a שחיטה, shechita
the second guy is not restricted by אותו ואת בנו. osso ve'es
beno, If he's not restricted by אותו ואת בנו osso ve'es beno,
and he's shechting it out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. he
gets כרת kareis because it could be brought inside the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So therefore, שני מקבל בפנים הוא. sheini mekabel bifnim hu.
So the second קרבן korban can be accepted in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Because if really קרבנות korbanos is excluded from אותו ואת
בנו, osso ve'es beno כרת נמי ליחייב, kareis nami lachayev, he should
also get כרת. kareis. So how do you explain it all together?
ואמר רבא, Va'amar Rava, so says Rava, ואיכא דאמרי, ve'ika de'amri, and
some say it was said anonymously, חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasurei mechasra
vehachi katani. The only way that we could possibly read this is
say it's missing some words and here's how you read it. קדשים,
kodshim.
if you have קרבנות, korbanot, שניהם בחוץ, shneihem bachutz, if you bring
both of them out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. לרבנן ענוש
כרת, Lerabbanan anush kareis, so for the rabbis the first guy gets
כרת. kareis. So, ראשון ענוש כרת rishon anush kareis because he brought
a קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, שני, Sheini,
the second guy, פסול, pasul, the animal's invalid because it was a
קרבן korban, that was out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. ופטור,
upatur, but you don't get כרת kareis because of the prohibition of
אותו ואת בנו, osso ve'es beno. right? Because of אותו ואת בנו,
osso ve'es beno, the second one could not be brought in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, מדלאו דשחוטי חוץ, Midlav deshchutei chutz, because he
is exempt from the prohibition of shech... he gets lashes for
אותו ואת בנו, osso ve'es beno but he doesn't get lashes for
shechting out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. right? Because this is
a... if he doesn't get lashes... וחכמים סברי vachachamim savri if there's
no כרת kareis there's no lashes. Okay, so meaning here's the case:
קרבנות korbanot. out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So what's the
story? According to the rabbis, nothing special. They're not bothered with שחיטה
שאינה ראויה. shechita she'einah re'uyah So they say the first guy gets
כרת kareis for bringing a קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash The second guy is prohibited by אותו ואת בנו osso
ve'es beno, because they're not bothered with שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'einah
re'uyah. So he transgresses אותו ואת בנו. osso ve'es beno. But because
he transgresses אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et bno. he doesn't transgress bringing
a קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. because this
is a קרבן korban that could not be brought today in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, That's what the rabbis say. What would Rebbi
Shimon say? If Rebbi Shimon really held of the position that שחיטת
קדשים shchitas kodashim does not count as שחיטה? shechita So... so here's
how we would have
to
say:
לרבי שמעון, Lerebbi Shimon, according to Rebbi Shimon, שניהם ענושים כרת. shneihem
anushim kareis. They both get כרת. kareis. Why? The first guy did
שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. And... but for אותו ואת בנו oto v'et
bno, it doesn't count as שחיטה. shechita Since it doesn't count as
שחיטה, Shechita the second guy also gets שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz because
it could be brought today as a קרבן. korban So they both
get כרת. kareis. אחד בחוץ ואחד בפנים, Echad bachutz ve'echad bifnim, yeah,
you thought we were done with this in our Mishnah, we got
to do it one more time. Okay, if one of them is
outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash the first קרבן, korban and the
next one inside. How will this work? So לרבנן ראשון ענוש כרת,
lerabbanan rishon anush kareis, the first guy gets כרת kareis for שחוטי
חוץ, shchutei chutz, obviously shechted קרבן korban outside. The second guy, he
wants to bring a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash,
today. Can he do it according to the rabbis? No, because of
אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et bno. right? They say we're not bothered
with שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'einah rauyah. You're restricted by אותו ואת
בנו. oto v'et bno. So the second guy, he doesn't get any
prohibition of שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, he's bringing it in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but it's still פסול. pasul. Oh for God's sake.
שני פסול ופטור, Sheini pasul upatur, the second guy, it's פסול, pasul,
it's invalid. valid, but you are exempt, okay, because of what do
you call it, because it because it cannot be brought as a
קרבן korban because of אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et bno. Oh, excuse
me, just one second. Stupid, stupid
camera. I've got to get a new camera. I don't know what
the heck is going on here. I'm sorry, buddy. Alright,
I think this is a bit better.
Okay, well, I think that ended that.
Alright, just give me one
second here again.
I'm sorry. We've got to get some... okay, so, right. Okay, so
therefore, so if they were one without, one without outside, one was
inside, the first guy you get כרת, kares, the second guy for
the רבנן Rabbanan is restricted by אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et bno,
so even though you're doing it in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
it's invalid because of אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et bno, Now for
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, what's the story with רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon,
שני כשר. sheini kasher. So the first guy of course nobody debates,
the first guy shechted out of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, so
the first guy gets transgresses שחוטי חוץ. sh'chutei chutz. The second guy,
however, for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, any שחיטת קרבן shechitat korban is
not included in אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et bno So the second
guy, it's a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash wonderful,
not restricted and it's a כשר קרבן. kasher korban. Except it's reversed,
אחד בפנים ואחד בחוץ, echad bifnim v'echad bachutz, one in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash, and one outside of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash.
so same thing except you reverse the order. So the first one
of course is a כשר קרבן, kasher korban, it's a קרבן korban
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, So what's the story with the
second? So let's take a look. So the רבנן, Rabbanan, ראשון כשר
פטור, rishon kasher patur, the first one's a כשר קרבן. kasher korban.
שני, sheini, the second guy which is a קרבן korban out of
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, according to the rabbis it's restricted by
אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et bno Because it's restricted by אותו ואת
בנו, oto v'et bno you don't get transgress for שחוטי חוץ, sh'chutei
chutz, right? Right? Because if it's restricted by אותו ואת בנו, oto
v'et bno so you say for אותו ואת בנו oto v'et bno,
but not for שחוטי חוץ. sh'chutei chutz. We're focusing on שחוטי חוץ,
sh'chutei chutz, okay. שני פסול ופטור, sheini pasul u'patur, you're exempt for
שחוטי חוץ. sh'chutei chutz. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon according to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, since there's no אותו ואת בנו oto v'et bno by
קרבנות, korbanot. so the first guy brought a good קרבן korban and
the second guy there's no restrictions. So if he brings it out
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he gets transgresses שחוטי חוץ. sh'chutei
chutz.
One minute, שני בלא תעשה.
sheini be'lo ta'aseh. But the only thing is, we're now going to
try to make sense, so all of this was a rewriting of
this ברייתא beraita to make it work with the assumption that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not apply, that אותו ואת בנו oto v'et
bno does not apply by קרבנות. korbanot, But now we are still,
so we've explained what all of the consequences would be if אותו
ואת בנו oto v'et bno doesn't apply by קרבנות. korbanot But we're
still stuck on the last line. Because if it doesn't apply by
קרבנות, korbanot. why is he saying here that when the first שחיטה
Shechita, was a כשר קרבן, kasher korban, the second thing is only
a negative prohibition? If it doesn't apply, אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et
bno then you're bringing the second one out of the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash that should be a full עונש כרת. onesh kares. So
it's a long way of saying, meaning it was a little bit
funny that they had to rewrite the whole ברייתא beraita because in
the end the question is the same question we began with. If
אותו ואת בנו oto v'et bno does not apply by קרבנות korbanot.
because it doesn't count as the שחיטה, Shechita then how can you
have the case that a קרבן korban, outside the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash, is not כשר kasher today but will be כשר kasher tomorrow?
אותו ואת בנו oto v'et bno. does not apply. So if it
doesn't apply, it's always כשר kasher today, and if it's always כשר
kasher today, then you always should get כרת. kares. Okay, so that
is our question, so we're back to the question we started with.
I'm sorry, what did you want?
I just wanted to review one point. Yeah. בפנים bifnim because you
have to throw the blood, that's the reason why?
Yes, because you have to throw the blood, yes.
Okay, so basically what we have is we have the statement that
we had yesterday that according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon because you
have to throw the blood of a קרבן, korban it doesn't count
as a שחיטה Shechita and therefore אותו ואת בנו oto v'et bno.
would never apply by קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, but now we have another
statement of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says if you have a
שחיטה shechting of a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash
because אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bno makes it prohibited today, so
you don't get כרת kares but you do get lashes for שחיטה
shechita outside. So you see אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bno, does
apply to קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so we rewrote the whole ברייתא beraita
but we're left with the same question, right? We rewrote it to
work with this idea, but in the end we're still saying we're
still stuck, it clearly does apply to קרבנות. korbanot, So how can
you say it does not? Yes.
I'm trying to understand רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon reasoning as to why
would he
separate, say if you're not going to eat it, then you can
do the אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es bno You know, according to
him what reason could the תורה have given not to do this?
Right, I
mean, I'm not sure, you see this gets again to this question
similar like to what you know, because I know you are always
sort of trying to bring in the question like what's the reason
for the מצוה, what's the reason for the details. And sometimes the
גמרא, you know, does sort of try to bring that in, like
it did a little bit by the question of is the father
included in the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es bno? But
very often the גמרא deals with formal categories, like even if I
could give you a reason for example here, let's say I said
that it's somehow a more callous act if you're doing it... for
the sake of just consumption and you know and or something like
that, but even if I could give you a reason here, the
point of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, is that he applies this across
the board, anytime there's a concept of שחיטה shechting in the תורה
it has to be it has to be fit. So whether it's
when you're חייב four or five, when you steal a שור shoar
or an ox, you know, anytime the תורה speaks about a שחיטה,
shechita. if you know, if you שחט shecht an animal, do you
have to cover the blood? Anytime שחיטה shechita always means a שחיטה
shechita that is fit for consumption. So that's like a very universal
definition, so it's hard to think that you have to each time
it will fit into the particular logic of that מצוה. You know,
so sometimes you find that. I mean I would say more often
than not the גמרא deals with formal definitions and is not always
saying well what's the reason of this מצוה and does it explain
this, you know, this exception and that exception. You know, that's why
I think some people, for some people that's something that's very attractive
of the גמרא, it's all the formal categories or whatever, and other
people there can be a frustrating element that it's not more trying
to bring in, you know, what's the reason behind it. But I
think there's it's true in general in law, you know, when when
a court tries to decide what exactly are the parameters of a
law, how often does it try to ask the big question about
what's this law all about, and how much how often does it
ask the more formal and technical questions about how these phrases are
understood and interpreted and what's their sort of classic meaning. So the
גמרא is much more often formal than it is reason-based.
It goes to those people who use this prohibition to show mercy.
Right, we're back to that. Right, exactly. Well, I'm not saying it's
totally off-base. No, look, I'm not saying it's totally off-base. The רמב"ם
Rambam says, and with this we'll have to move on, the רמב"ם
Rambam says in his
in the מורה נבוכים, Moreh Nevuchim, in the third חלק chelek where
he discusses the reasons for the מצוות, mitzvot, he says I'm going
to give you the bit broad-stroke reasons. He says, don't ask me
for the reasons for details. Any law needs to have details and
parameters and you're not going to have the reason work with all
the details or necessarily translated to all the details. Now, there were
others that disagreed, רב סעדיה גאון Rav Saadia Gaon I believe tried
to give reasons for even all the details of the laws. But
the רמב"ם Rambam says, I can tell you the reason for קרבנות.
korbanot, Don't start asking me why this קרבן korban, is a ram,
and this one is a sheep, and this one is a cow,
and this one is male, and this one is female, and this
one is seven, and this one is whatever. He says, that's not,
everything has to have details, but we can talk about big big-picture
reasons. So here, the big-picture reason is not contradicted by the fact
that there are certain formal limitations. Okay, you just say it doesn't
translate into all the details, but it's not a contradiction to the
broad-stroke reason. Okay, so that is I think normally how the גמרא
operates is that it has, you know, details and parameters which it
doesn't try to work into the reason, but I don't think it's
as much of a problem unless it really contradicts the reason. But
I
think that's the general whether you like it or not, I think
that's the general approach of the גמרא.
Alright, so let's take a look now as we continue. So the
גמרא says, okay, ואי סלקא דעתך ve'ee salka daitach אינו אותו ואת
בנו נוהג בקדשים, eino oso ve'es bno noheg bekodshim, if you really
think it doesn't apply by קרבנות, korbanot which we implicitly said now
when we tried to rewrite the whole ברייתא, baraita, so שני אמאי
בלא תעשה, sheni amai belo sa'aseh, why again, how could the second
guy get off and only get a negative prohibition and not get
כרת? kares? ותו לא, v'sulo, and not nothing more? כרת נמי ליחייב,
kares nami litchayav, let him also get כרת. kares. So we're back
to the question we started with. How could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
say the second guy who brings a קרבן korban out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because you know,
he transgresses שחיטה shechita, outside, but it's not so bad because it
can't be brought today, so you don't get כרת kares and you
get a לאו? If אותו ואת בנו oso v'es b'no, isn't a
restriction for קרבנות, korbanot, then there should not be a problem altogether.
I mean not be a problem, then he should get the full
prohibition, כרת, kares, because there's no restriction. So the גמרא says, אלא
אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather says רבא, Rava, and with
this we reject what we said yesterday that קדשים kodshim, is excluded
from אותו ואת בנו, oso v'es b'no is not considered שחיטה ראויה,
shechita reu'yah, and we're going to say קדשים kodshim, is שחיטה ראויה.
shechita reu'yah. Rather, here's what רבא Rava says, הכי קאמר רב המנונא,
hachi ka'amar Rav Hamnuna, this is what רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna says,
אין מלקות אותו ואת בנו נוהג בקדשים, ein malkus oso ve'es bno
noheg bekodshim,
I'll grant you there's no lashes for אותו ואת בנו oso v'es
b'no by קדשים, only in certain cases. What? כיון דכמה דלא זריק
דם לא משתרי בשר, keivan d'kamah delo zarik dam, lo mishtari basar,
because the meat is not yet permitted. So therefore if I שחט
shecht, קרבן korban, number one and then I שחט shecht קרבן korban
number two before I threw the blood of קרבן korban number one,
I can't say I've done a שחיטה shechita, yet for קרבן korban
number one because the meat was not yet permitted. And therefore I'm
off the hook for שחיטה shechita קרבן korban. two because קרבן korban
one does not yet count as a שחיטה. shechita, Let's say I
threw the blood for קרבן korban number one and now I'm שחט
shecht קרבן korban. number two, do I transgress אותו ואת בנו? oso
v'es b'no. Maybe, maybe not. What's going to determine whether this second
שחיטה shechita. was a שחיטה shechita or not?
Whether I'll be זורק בדם.
zorek badam. So what right, if I don't if I'm not זורק
בדם zorek badam and the meat never became permissible, then it wasn't
a שחיטה, shechita so I will never be able to give me
lashes. lashes for שחטing shecht a קרבן korban, for אותו ואת בנו,
oso v'es b'no because you never know at that moment whether I'm
definitely going to transgress or not. I might be זורק הדם, zorek
hadam, I might not be זורק הדם. zorek hadam.
So what happens if you do?
Then I transgressed, but in order to get lashes you have to
warn me at the moment of the transgression. So I will have
transgressed, but you'll never be able to give me lashes, because at
the moment of the transgression of the שחיטה, shechita? you don't know
whether it will be a שחיטה shechita, or not. Okay. So what?
If somebody brought two קרבנות korbanot at the same time?
Of the same animal, a mother and a child on the same
day? Well, according to what we were saying earlier, according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon yes, but now we're rejecting that. Now we're saying
no. Okay, so as opposed to saying that it's a שחיטה, shechita
it's not a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'einah rauyah, the גמרא before
saying it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechita she'einah rauyah, because it doesn't
by itself allow it. You could have gone to the opposite extreme
and said it's a שחיטה ראויה shechita reuya because it's a necessary
part of allowing. We're taking a middle position. It will be, whether
it's a שחיטה ראויה shechita reuya or not will be determined based
on whether you're זורק הדם. zorek hadam. So but yes, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon. does say that אותו ואת בנו oso v'es b'no. applies
to קרבנות, korbanot but he'll just say you'll never be able to
get lashes, because at the moment of transgression you won't know whether
it's a שחיטה ראויה shechita reuya or not. Okay.
But isn't there another transgression? Well, if I say of a side
sin of a side sin? Right. Can he bring two קרבן, korban,
two קרבנות korbanot for the same thing?
No, you can't bring two קרבנות korbanot for the same sin, but
you can bring two קרבנות korbanos? for separate sins on the same
day, one for a sin and one for a free-will offering, but
not two קרבנות korbanos for the same sin. Yeah. Wait. Why can't
you warn right before he throws the blood? Because then you've already
done the transgression. The warning has to precede the transgression. The transgression
was the שחיטה. shechita. The throwing of the blood retroactively shows you
that the שחיטה shechita counted. Okay, but the transgression of אותו ואת
בנו oso v'es b'no? is to שחט. shecht But whether that counts
as שחיטה shechita will
only be determined later when you throw the blood.
So before the שחיטה? shechita, It's too early. If you warn before
the שחיטה, shechita it's not definite that you're going to transgress. You're
never definitely going to transgress until you warn. No, but you say
don't do it, and he says yes, and then he does the
act that immediately follows, that act has to be the transgression.
It's two separate acts involved.
Exactly. And the first act is the transgression, but the second act
determines whether
the first act counted or not. Yes, question? Is there a sense
of doing שחיטה shechita and not throwing the blood? Is that... Yes,
as I was just saying. The transgression is שחטing shecht אותו ואת
בנו. oso v'es bno Throwing the blood is not the transgression. I'm
sure there's no thing, is there a separate transgression here, it's... No,
there's no transgression of throwing the blood. The transgression is only שחיטה.
shechita But whether it was a שחיטה shechita, is determined by whether
you throw the blood. See, I don't like these kind of things,
I think we dealt with it before, like you know, say like
listen, don't שחט, shecht no matter what you shouldn't be שחטing shecht
it, and especially if you do throw the blood then you get
מלקות. malkos. He's like warning him that. Okay, but it's not enough
to get מלקות. malkos, מלקות malkos has to be that I know
the act I'm about to do is definitely going to get me
מלקות. malkos Okay, but fine, we'll talk about it more when we
do
סנהדרין Sanhedrin and we do התראת ספק. Hasra'at Safek. Okay, let's move.
Okay, so anyway the גמרא says you can't get מלקות. malkus.
כיון דכמה דלא זרק דם לא
משתרי בשר,
keivan de'kama d'lo zarek dam
lo mishtarei basar,
since as long as the blood has not been thrown the meat
is not permissible. ובעידן דקא שחיט u-be-idan de-ka-shachit from the moment you're
doing the שחיטה shechita.
of the second one, and you're doing a prohibited act,
הוי התראת ספק, havei hasra'at safek, the warning is doubtful, והתראת ספק
לא שמה התראה ve-hasra'at safek lo shema hasra'a and it does not
count as warning.
So now first of all we can rest a little
bit easier because we're not saying that שחיטת קדשים shechitat kodshim doesn't
count. We're saying it will count when you throw the blood.
And now we understand that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, does say אותו
ואת בנו oso v'es bno applies by קדשים. Okay, you won't get
מלקות, but it applies. And now we understand why if I שחט
shecht a קרבן Korban outside the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and I שחטed shecht the mother today, why I don't
transgress שחוטי חוץ? shuchutei chutz? Because I am prohibited to שחט shecht
this קרבן Korban today for אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es beno. The
prohibition does apply. Okay, and since the prohibition does apply, don't שחט
shecht it and sprinkle the blood, it applies under certain circumstances. Therefore
if I, it's not fit to be brought as a קרבן, Korban
and therefore I don't fully transgress שחוטי חוץ. shuchutei chutz. I get
a לאו, but I don't get כרת kares because this cannot be
brought as a קרבן Korban today because I cannot שחט shecht it
and sprinkle the blood. Okay, ואזדא רבא לטעמיה, ve-azda Rava le-taamei, רבא
Rava goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רבא, de-amar Rava, because רבא
Rava says, היא חולין ובנה שלמים, hee chullin u-vena shlamim, if you
have a case where the mother is a חולין chullin and the
child is a שלמים, shlamim, שחט חולין ואחר כך שחט שלמים, shachat
chullin v'achar kach shachat shlamim,
so you שחטed shechted
the
חולין chullin
so
that's unquestionably a שחיטה, shechita and then you שחטed shechted the קרבן,
now you're שחטing shechted the קרבן I should mention in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, here, we're not doing שחוטי חוץ. shuchutei chutz. You
שחטed shechted the קרבן in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash have you
transgressed אותו ואת בנו? oso ve'es beno That's an easy one. What's
the story? I'm sorry, you have transgressed but you're not going to
get מלקות because at the moment of שחיטה shechita. we don't know
will you be זורק הדם? zorek hadam? So פטור. patur. So you're
exempt from מלקות because at the moment of שחיטה shechita. we don't
know. This is all according to רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon שלמים ואחר
חולין, shlamim v'achar chullin, first you שחטed shecht the קרבן in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? and you sprinkled the blood. So the first
שחיטה shechita, now we know counted because you sprinkled the blood. And
now after you sprinkled the blood you come to שחט shecht the
חולין, chullin, the non-קרבן. חייב now you transgress. Okay, so yes, according
to רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, it can be a שחיטה, shechita we'll
know after you sprinkle the blood. If that happened with the first
animal then by the time you get to the second you know
that you had a full שחיטה. shechita, But if it happens by
the second animal, you'll never get lashes because at the moment of
transgression we don't know if the blood will be sprinkled. Second animal
was outside the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash, Yeah, but it was חולין,
chullin, right. חולין. chullin. דאמר רבא, De'amar Rava,
רבא Rava also said, and this is a point that Avigail isn't
here but she raised this question yesterday: what is the story according
to
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, about an עולה?
Olah? Is that considered שחיטה ראויה shechita re'uyah because you can't eat
the meat? Okay. היא חולין ובנה עולה, hee chullin u'vnah Olah, let's
say the mother is a חולין chullin and the child, we're assuming
the child is second, is an עולה. Olah. So that's like, that's
a no-brainer because we always know when the
second animal is קדשים, you never get lashes because you don't know
at the moment of שחיטה shechita, whether it will count or not.
לא מיבעיא lo mibaya שחט חולין ואחר כך שחט עולה, shachat chullin
v'achar kach shachat Olah, it goes without saying that if first you
שחט shecht the חולין chullin and then you שחט shecht the עולה
Olah in the בית המקדש, Bais HaMikdash, פטור, patur, you're exempt. Why?
Because we know when the second animal is קדשים, according to רבי
שמעון, Rebbe Shimon you can never get lashes because we don't know
at that moment if you'll sprinkle the blood. אלא, ella, but rather,
אפילו שחט עולה ואחר כך שחט חולין, afilu shachat Olah v'achar kach
shachat chullin, if now at the top of the עמוד ב', even
if you שחט shecht the עולה Olah and then you שחט shecht
the חולין. chullin. So before we said, you שחט shecht the קרבן
first, you sprinkle the blood, then by the time you get to
the second one, you know you've already done a שחיטה. shechting He
says by עולה Olah that won't work, because by עולה, Olah, even
if you sprinkle the blood, you can't eat the meat.
So by an עולה Olah it never counts as a שחיטה. shechita
Okay. פטור, patur,
you're exempt. Why? שחיטה כמאן דלא
שחיטה בת אכילה היא. shechita kman d'lo shechita bas achilah hee. The
first שחיטה, shechita even though you sprinkled the blood, never made the
meat permissible. So it will, according to רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon. will
never be a שחיטה ראויה. shechita re'uyah.
Who says it has to be for אכילה, achilah,
as we just...
Well, okay, that's what we're assuming.
שחיטה ראויה shechita re'uyah normally means אכילה, achilah, right? What do you
mean? You can eat it. But now the גמרא is going to
say the other thing. רב יעקב אמר רב יוחנן, Rav Yaakov amar
Rav Yochanan. רב יעקב Rav Yaakov said in the name of רב
יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, אכילת מזבח שמה אכילה. achilas mizbeach shema achilah.
It's funny, this is what Avigail asked yesterday. She was channeling רבא
Rava and I was channeling רב יעקב Rav Yaakov אמר רב יוחנן.
amar Rav Yochanan, Yes, the fact that the meat can be eaten,
it doesn't have to be
eaten,
it's not just can be used, but eaten by the altar is
considered an eating. Okay. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reasoning? דאמר
קרא, ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו, v'im he'achol ye'achel mibesar zevach
shlamav, if the meat will be eaten, this is a פסוק pasuk
about פיגול, pigul, and we say בשתי אכילות הכתוב מדבר, bishtei achilos
hakatuv m'daber, talking about two types of eating. אחת אכילת אדם ואחת
אכילת מזבח. achas achilas adam v'achas achilas mizbeach. Your פיגול pigul thoughts,
since you never escape פיגול pigul even when we dwell into חולין,
chullin, your פיגול pigul thoughts make a קרבן invalid whether they're plans
about eating it at the wrong time or burning it on the
altar at the wrong time. That also counts as אכילה. achilah. So
what have we said now? The upshot of all of this about
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, and שחיטה shechita שאינה ראויה re'uyah was, does
it apply to קרבנות? korbanos There's one opinion that it's always אינה
ראויה einah re'uyah by קרבנות korbanos. because the meat does not become
permissible immediately. And according to that, אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es beno
doesn't apply to קרבנות korbanos according to רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. You'll
never have a שחיטה ראויה shechita re'uyah when you're dealing with a
קרבן. Then we had what seemed a little bit extreme, and then
we had the positions at the end of רבא Rava which made
a lot more sense, I think, which is that it does apply,
but not that it definitely applies, it will be based on whether
the meat becomes permissible, based on whether you sprinkle the blood. So
therefore, if it's the first animal that was a קרבן, you can
transgress by the second animal. If it's the second, you can never
get lashes because at the moment of שחיטה shechita. you don't know
whether or not you will transgress. Yes. And now if you might
have thought we're done with רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon's now we actually
turn to the next משנה, which is the explicit position of רבי
שמעון. Rebbe Shimon's Until now we've just been bringing him in, it
actually gets front and center in this next משנה. Yes, question? Yeah,
I mean, I think, you know, because it says לא תשחטו lo
sishchatu and I understand it needs to be, you know, to be
ראויה re'uyah, for what its purposes are. So basically, it's not necessarily...
All right, but the question is we haven't seen the basis of
רבי שמעון's Rebbe Shimon position. And one of the פסוקים pesukim the
גמרא quotes for רבי שמעון's position is טבוח טבח והכן, tvoach tevach
v'hachen, which is not a word about שחיטה, shechita, but it's another
word for שחיטה, shechita, טבוח, tvoach, and there we're talking about a
case of שחיטה shechita, something to be fit for eating. So according
to רבנן rabbanan then you don't have any of this problem, so
it wouldn't make a difference whether it was... Right. And according to
רבנן rabbanan none of this... and it's inclusive of just a קרבן,
it's any time. Right. And let's read, thank you. So let's read
the next משנה. השוחט ונמצא טרפה, hashocheit v'nimtza tereifah, this is the
משנה of שחיטה shechita שאינה ראויה. The גמרא was bringing it in,
but this is the משנה. You שחט shecht an animal טרפה, tereifah,
which is forbidden to eat, not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, but still
forbidden to eat. השוחט לעבודה זרה, hashocheit l'avodah zarah, or you שחט
shecht it for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right, which now makes it
an offering to עבודה זרה avodah zarah and forbidden in benefit. השוחט
פרת חטאת, hashocheit parat chatas, or you שחט shecht a פרה אדומה,
parah adumah, which obviously you cannot benefit from a פרה אדומה. parah
adumah. ושור הנסקל, v'shor haniskal, or an ox that gored and has
to be stoned, which cannot be benefited from. עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah,
calf that has to be broken the neck in the ואדי, wadi,
which there's a certain stage where it gets the status even before
the neck is broken. So if you שחט shecht and it's therefore
forbidden in benefit. רבי שמעון פוטר, Rebbe Shimon poter, in all these
cases רבי שמעון says you're off the hook for אותו ואת בנו
oso ve'es beno. because it is a שחיטה shechta that is not
ראויה, fit for eating. וחכמים מחייבים, v'chachamim mechayvim, and the rabbis say
you have transgressed. So here it is, it was all our discussion.
So here it is, it was all our discussion in the last
day and a half, but it's all explicit in this משנה that
the איסור issur of שחיטה shechita שאינה ראויה. Now, here's one case
the rabbis agree to. השוחט ונמצא נבלה בידו, hashochet venimtza neveilah beyado,
you שחט shecht and accidentally you mess up the שחיטה shechita and
you make it a נבלה, neveilah, so that's not just it was
a שחיטה shechisah, that did not make the meat permissible, it doesn't
count as a שחיטה. shechisah If you mess up the act of
a שחיטה, the animal is considered a נבלה neveilah and therefore not
a שחיטה, just like you killed it. That everybody agrees you do
not transgress. והנוחר והמעקר, vehanocher vehameaker, נוחר nocher is a way of
like killing an animal without even dealing with the סימנים, simanim, or
you pull out the סימנים. simanim. In all these cases where you
unintentionally or intentionally kill it in a way that is not a
שחיטה, everybody agrees פטור משום אותו ואת בנו. pattur mishum oso ve'es
beno. You do not transgress אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es beno. Might
be צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, but you don't transgress אותו
ואת בנו oso ve'es beno? because that doesn't count as a שחיטה
at all. Okay, now the גמרא, since we've already spent a lot
of time on שחיטה שאינה ראויה, the גמרא's going to shift its
focus to a more a different and quite interesting question, which is
when you שחט לעבודה זרה. la'avodah zarah. Should your sin of being
עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, you know, supersede any other considerations
of אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es beno. and so on. So let's
take a look. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, so said ריש
לקיש: Reish Lakish: לא שנו, lo shanu, when is it the rabbis
say that when you שחט לעבודה זרה la'avodah zarah you still transgress?
אלא ששחט ראשון לעבודה זרה ושני לשולחנו. ella sheshachat rishon la'avodah zarah
vesheni leshulchano. The first one was שחט לעבודה זרה, la'avodah zarah, so
that sin was over and done with, and the second one, either
you could even be a second person, but whatever, the first sin
is history, and now the second animal, that you're שחיטה-ing for meat.
In that type of a case, the first שחיטה counted as a
שחיטה and your second thing and you're חייב משום אותו ואת בנו.
chayav mishum oso ve'es beno. אבל ראשון לשולחנו ושני לעבודה זרה, aval
rishon leshulchano vesheni la'avodah zarah, so if the first one was שחט
for meat and the second one for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, so
forget שחיטה שאינה ראויה, you're off the hook פטור, pattur, why? דקמליה
בדרבה מיניה. dekam lei bidrabba minei. You get the bigger punishment. This
act of שחט-ing this animal for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you did
two acts: you did an act of worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and you did a transgression of אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es beno.
So the act of עבודה זרה avodah zarah is a little bit
bigger and therefore you give the guy the bigger punishment, קמליה בדרבה
מיניה, kam lei bidrabba minei, you establish it with the bigger one.
Do you get כרת? kares? No, you get... for עבודה זרה? avodah
zarah? Yeah, you get מיתה, misah, you get executed. So that transcend,
that obviously takes precedence and that's the principle of if you do
one act with two punishments, you give him the bigger punishment. קמליה
בדרבה מיניה, Kam lei bidrabba minei, you establish it with the bigger
one. So, אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to ריש לקיש: Reish Lakish: זו אפילו תינוקות
של בית רבן יודעים. zu afilu tinokos shel beis rabban yodim. This
even schoolchildren know that point. So, normally it's ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
that's giving רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan a hard time, here רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says: That's nothing. Oh my god, everybody knows קמליה בדרבה
מיניה, kam lei bidrabba minei, right? So therefore, I'm sure everybody here
was ready to ask me that question. So anyway, אלא, ella, he
says, פעמים
שאפילו שחט ראשון לשולחנו
ושני לעבודה זרה חייב. pe'amim
she'afilu shachat rishon leshulchano
vesheni la'avodah zarah chayav. You should have told me that there are
ways in which even if the second
one was
עבודה זרה avodah zarah you could still transgress אותו ואת בנו. oso
ve'es beno. You should have told me the exception. What's the exception?
How could the second guy who's doing it לעבודה זרה la'avodah zarah
also get אותו ואת בנו? oso ve'es beno, כגון דאתרו ביה משום
אותו ואת בנו ולא אתרו ביה משום עבודה זרה. kegon de'asru bei
mishum oso ve'es beno velo asru bei mishum avodah zarah. Before he
שחט-ed, they did, they were focused on אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es
bno. Maybe they didn't even know that he was planning on doing
it לעבודה זרה. la'avodah zarah. Who knows what their issue was? But
they only warned him for the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. Beno
So since we're not going to be, you're not going to be
deserving of the death penalty 'cause you didn't get the right warning
for that, and therefore you can't get that punishment, so then we
don't say that that supersedes, and therefore you will get the punishment
of אותו ואת בנו. Beno It also requires two witnesses? Yes, any
corporal punishment, lashes or מיתה misah requires two witnesses. Okay, ולא,, velo,
okay. ורבי שמעון בן לקיש, veRabbi Shimon ben Lakish, ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, why did he not say this? Presumably he has a reason
he didn't give, he didn't speak about this case. אמר, he would
say, כיון דכי אתרו ביה פטור, keivan dechi asru bei pattur, since
were you to warn him for עבודה זרה avodah zarah you'd be
exempt from אותו ואת בנו, Beno כי לא אתרו ביה נמי פטור,
ki lo asru bei nami pattur, even without the warning, the presence
of a sin that is worthy of the death penalty supersedes other
sins and other transgressions. And this is a general debate about the
principle of קמליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei bidrabba minei. קמליה בדרבה מיניה
Kam lei bidrabba minei in its simplest form is if we actually
are going to give you a punishment, we're going to give you
one punishment and not two and we'll give you the bigger one.
Okay? That's learned from the פסוק pasuk כדי רשעתו במספר, kedei rishaso
bemispar, רשעה אחת אתם מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו בשתי רשעויות, risha achas
atem mechayvo ve'ee attah mechayvo bishtei risha'uyos, that you only punish a
person for one act, you only give them one punishment, so you'll
give them the bigger one. That's the simple case. That's what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said: anytime you're not giving one punishment, you're free
to give the others. But comes along ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and
says that's not the only case. There are also cases where, and
especially cases of the death penalty, where the presence of the other
sin overshadows the smaller sin. And if this act had, had incorporated
into it a sin that you would get מיתה, misah, that com...
completely overshadows the smaller sin of אותו ואת בנו. Beno. And therefore,
even if we're not going to punish you for it, it's like
you can't even relate to the smaller sin in the presence of
the bigger one. And therefore, yeah, you get off scot-free in that
case as well. God will take care of you, but well yes,
okay, but yes, God will take care of you, but in terms
of בית דין, beis din, we can't even relate to the smaller
sin in the presence of the bigger one. Because no witnesses, because
there were not warnings for the bigger one, so you're not going
to get punished, but it still overshadows the smaller one. That's ריש
לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's position. ואזדו לטעמייהו, V'azdu l'taamayuuh, they go according to
their reasonings because they've articulated this debate elsewhere. דכי אתא רב דימי,
De-ki asa Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he reported the following. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר,
De-ki asa Rav Dimi amar, he said, חייבי מיתות שוגגין, chayvei misos
shoggin, if you do a sin that is worthy of the death
penalty, a capital crime, but you do it unintentionally. Now that's even
less severe than doing it willfully without warning. Right, willfully without warning,
at least you're deserving of the death penalty but you got off.
Here, if you did it even unwittingly, unintentionally, the sin is a
weighty sin, but you were never worthy of the death penalty, you
did it בשוגג, be-shogeg, and nevertheless, and you did that together with
another sin. Or חייבי מלקיות שוגגין, chayvei malkiyos shoggegin, or you did
something that's worthy of lashes, but you did it unintentionally, so you
never were deserving of lashes, it wasn't just a technicality. Nevertheless, if
you do it together with דבר אחר, davar acher, something else. What's
the something else? No, no, no. Here the something else means a
civil liability because lashes will never supersede lashes. So what's weaker than
lashes? Money. So if you did a sin worthy of the death
penalty even by accident, or sin worthy of lashes even unintentionally, even
by accident, and at the same time you were doing something, a
civil liability, like you were you shot a guy by accident and
you bloodied his shirt. Okay, or or you... that would be an
example. What's מלקיות שוגגין? malkiyos shoggegin? On יום טוב, Yom Tov, you
destroyed somebody's property. Okay, so it's יום טוב, Yom Tov, you did
a... you'd have to do a case where that wouldn't be מקלקל.
mekalkel. But whatever. Anyway, you did something that you get lashes at
the same time you're destroying property. So the presence of the bigger
sin overshadows the civil liability. Okay, that's what he says. So what's
the story there? רבי יוחנן אמר חייב, Rabbi Yochanan amar chayiv, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it does not overshadow. If you're not getting
punished, then it's irrelevant. וריש לקיש אמר פטור, v'Reish Lakish amar patur,
you're exempt. רבי יוחנן אמר חייב, Rabbi Yochanan amar chayiv, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says you still you do the lesser thing. דהלו לא
אתרו ביה, De-halo lo asru bei, you didn't get warning, and here
it's more than you didn't get warning, you didn't even do it
intentionally. So therefore it's not relevant. We're only... we're not going to
punish you for the first, we'll punish you for the second. וריש
לקיש אמר פטור, v'Reish Lakish amar patur, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
you're exempt. דכיון דאי אתרו ביה פטור, De-keivan de-ee asru bei patur,
since were you to give warning you'd be exempt, כי לא אתרו
ביה נמי פטור, ki lo asru bei nami patur, even without warning
you're also exempt. The sin overshadows. And again, what's even more surprising
here is that here it's not just about warning, here you even
did it בשוגג. be-shogeg. You did it unintentionally. So it's not like
you're deserving of the death penalty but we're not going to actually,
you know, take it out. You're not even deserving of the death
penalty, so it's really for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, it's much more
the sin overshadows, the act overshadows, rather than the punishment overshadows. Right?
For רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's we're not going to do two
punishments, but if we're not doing one, we'll do the other. You
could have said if you're deserving of the death penalty but you
got off, we're not going to make you do something else. But
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish goes even further. Even if you did it
unintentionally, even if you're not deserving, the very fact that you did
that weighty sin, even if without liability, the sin overshadows the lesser
thing, and therefore you're not going to have to do the lesser
the lesser liability. That's ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. With what's this? Yeah,
if they didn't warn you, you can be בשוגג be-shogeg with witnesses.
They happen to see you do something, they don't warn you. Or
with a warning? No, the whole purpose of התראה hasra-ah is to
exclude it from being שוגג. shogeg. Okay? All right, so now the
גמרא says like this. וצריכא, v'tzricha, now you need to state the
debate in both cases. Why? דאי אשמעינן, De-ee ashmiyinan, if you had
said בהא, be-ha, only in one case, בהא קאמר ריש לקיש, be-ha
ka-amar Reish Lakish, that's where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that it
overshadows. אבל בהא, Aval be-ha, in the other case, I'm specifically not
saying which is which, I'll talk about in a minute, אימא מודי
ליה לרבי יוחנן, eima modi leh l'Rabbi Yochanan, maybe he would agree
to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. ואי איתמר בהא, Ve-ee itmar be-ha, if
you had just said the other case, בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן, be-ha
ka-amar Rabbi Yochanan, that's where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that it's
only if you actually are being punished. אבל בהא, Aval be-ha, but
the other case, אימא מודי ליה לריש לקיש, eima modi leh l'Reish
Lakish, maybe he'd agree to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that it's even
if you're not being punished it's enough to overshadow, צריכא, tzricha, you
need both. Now, which is which? So here there's a debate between
which is the case that's more obvious, which is the case that's
less obvious according to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Here there's a debate
between רש״י Rashi and תוספות. רש״י says it is I would be
more inclined to think in a case where the two things... In
one case we had the big sin was מיתה misa and the
smaller sin was lashes. In the other cases we had the big
sin was מיתה misa or lashes and the smaller sin was ממון.
mammon. So the basic difference of the two cases is, is the
smaller sin lashes, or is the smaller sin money? So which case
is more obvious? So רש"י Rashi says when the smaller sin is
money, I would think that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would be more
inclined to say you're obligated. Why? Because then they are very much
categorically different types of punishments. One is a punishment of the court,
and the other is, and it's about things that we do to
your body, so we're not going to, like, so you know, maybe
those get sort of packaged together. And the other is a civil
liability that you have to another person. It's not even a punishment.
So I might think that according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, even
if one sin overshadows another sin, and especially when it's all about
ways we're going to punish your body, right? A sin and a
civil liability are very different things and therefore they don't overshadow, they
don't relate, and maybe there he would say that unless we're actually
punishing you, just the presence of the act without being punished is
not enough to overshadow a civil liability. That's what רש"י Rashi says.
In my mind that makes a lot of sense, right? Civil liability
should not be lumped together with issues about punishments of the court
and so on, certainly in a case where you're not really being
punished, it's just you did a big sin. So that's what רש"י
Rashi says. I might have thought that case ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
would have agreed to ר' יוחנן Reb Yochanan when it's about civil
liability. קמ"ל, Kamashmalan, no, that even if you've just done the sin
without being punished, it overshadows the civil liability. תוספות says the exact
opposite. תוספות says that payment of money is a, you know, is
a much more, if you would, weaker punishment, right? It's a, it's
a, it's a much lighter punishment. So if you just think about
the issue of light and heavy, it's much more clear that a
big sin completely overshadows something as trivial as a payment of money.
But maybe it wouldn't have overshadowed a punishment of lashes. Okay, so
that's the way תוספות says it. I might have thought that ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish would have agreed to ר' יוחנן Reb Yochanan that
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish only said his position when it was money,
that was, is easy to overshadow, but maybe when it's lashes, he
would say if you're not being punished for the big you should
be punished for the small, and it's telling us not that way.
So it's an interesting way of thinking about two very different ways
you could go here, but either way ר' יוחנן Reb Yochanan and
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish are consistent. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says the
big sin always overshadows, even if you didn't get warning, even if
you didn't do it intentionally, the presence of the big sin overshadows,
and therefore you're not going to get the smaller punishment, whether the
smallest punishment is lashes or money. And ר' יוחנן Reb Yochanan says
it's never about the sin, it's always about the punishment. If you're
getting punished for the big thing, we're not going to do the
small thing. If you're not going to get punished for the big
thing, you are going to have to deal with the consequences of
the small thing. Okay, we continue tomorrow. But the שור ושה Shor
Vasheh excludes בנו Beno. והחיה, VeHaChayah, what the שור ושה Shor Vasheh
says, right? So why can't we just say that the שור ושה
Shor Vasheh includes מיני קרבנות Minei Korbanot and it's not, and in
which case it's not it would include עופות? Ofot? What? No, it's
just like a שור Shor is a קרבן and a שה Seh
is a קרבן and what we're saying is not to exclude חיה,
Chayah, it's to include עופות Ofot in the provision of שור ושה.
Shor Vasheh. Just like a שור Shor is a קרבן and a
שה Seh is a קרבן include no, no, no, I've already said
that בנו is not the חז"ל Chazal refuse to see בנו in
the case of non-mammals if it doesn't give birth to it live,
it doesn't consider it to be בנו. I'm sorry, say it again,
the what? If it's non-mammals it does not give birth to live
young, it does not. But how do we know that? It's an
assumption that חז"ל curves, that they would not be called בנו. It's
an exit hatch. That's, that's the way. I do remember you saying
that but I don't know, like, how you do that, but I
guess it's just one of those things. Testing, testing. One, two, three,
four. Testing microphone. And this is the second take. אחת, שתיים, שלוש,
ארבע. achat, shtayim, shalosh, arba. Thank you. I had a question what
we were doing as well. So Rabbi Shimon says you'll never be
held responsible because you didn't throw the blood yet, right? Inside inside
the בית המקדש, you won't be a שוחט, shochet, right? Because you
didn't yet throw... Right, and Rava came later and said that sometimes
you will be. Well Rabbi Shimon never said anything about whether it
applies. Rabbi Shimon just said if it's not a fit שחיטה, you
don't transgress. And then Rava came and then there was a question
about how would that or would that not be relevant to קרבנות.
korbanos So one opinion says it is all קרבנות are always considered
not fit, and you would never transgress. And Rava comes and says
that what is it and Rava comes and says that no, it
only applies to קרבנות that are it only applies you do transgress
but in a case where no, sorry, you transgress but you don't
get מלקות. Okay, so he doesn't agree with this idea about never
have to have the blood thrown I mean in order to be
considered responsible for it. Rava. No, Rava says hold on. Oh, that's
דף sixty-two, I'm sorry. Okay, so I'm sorry, hold on. I'm sorry,
I didn't mean to. No, no, no, no, I just it looks
like we missed a part once, the picture of the thing. All
right, we have to go back. Yes, I'm sorry. So anyway, so
ask me your question. Rabbi Shimon says because you have not thrown
the blood yet, you won't be held responsible ever, right? And Rava
came later on and said that sometimes you are responsible. No, Rabbi
Shimon did not say anything about the blood. Rabbi Shimon said oh
wait a minute, I'm sorry. Hold on one minute. Sorry, sorry, sorry,
sorry. Rava came along and said Rabbi Shimon said if the שחיטה
is not fit, you're not responsible. Right.